Inland, Wetlands and
Water Corridors is commissioned to order,
and I'm going to try one more time to get my agenda to open. I'm having a little trouble with preview here.
Okay, so the first thing we have called to order,
the roll call seating of board alternates.
We have, I see on the call, Jed Larson
and William Monroe.
So we have quorum for the meeting,
and we can proceed then to see if there are any changes
or
revisions to the agenda. Are there any that anybody's aware of?
Okay, seeing none, I will proceed to approval of the minutes. Our last regular meeting with 07/13/2021,
and I'll ask for a motion to approve the minutes of that meeting.
>> I'll make a motion to approve the meeting minutes from July 13.
I second that.
>> Okay. Moved by Commissioner Larson, seconded by Commissioner Monroe
to approve the minutes. Are there any comments, revisions,
corrections
to enter into the record?
I had none.
>> Nor I.
Okay,
well, then I'll ask for a vote.
Commissioner Larson.
Aye.
>> Commissioner Monroe.
And I, Chairman Elliott,
also vote aye.
So the motion carries three zero zero.
Next item on the agenda.
I can get that to stay on my screen.
Okay, do we have any
wish for public comment?
I see only two members of the public at the meeting, and they have an item on the agenda coming up.
So,
move on
to new business.
Oh, and I failed to mention
to those not on the commission
that
due to an obligation to be at Bradley Airport,
I'm going to have to leave this meeting at 08:15,
so we're going to have to move right along.
Okay, so new business. So we have a jurisdictional
ruling review,
IWWC
20 one-fifteen,
parentheses JR,
from the town of Andover regarding
repairs
to the culverts on the Hawk River at Bunker Hill Road.
I
will make a motion
that the
Commission has jurisdiction
in regard
to this activity,
and I would like a second
to that motion.
Larson will second.
>> Okay, so I have a motion and a second. The reason I did that was because we're going to have to vote on it, and we might as well get the motion on the floor right away.
I see Eric Anderson, town administrator, on the call,
who will
speak to the issue on behalf of the town.
>> Sure.
So
the town submitted a wetlands
application
for a repair
of the triple culvert at Bunker Hill.
And George, can I share the screen?
Sure. If,
Abby will, handle that? I can't.
Not administering
the meeting. Can you enable
screen sharing for me?
Alright, you should be able to now.
>> Okay, yep, got it.
Okay.
So,
what you're looking at is a
diagram
of
the issues
that the town is having
with the Bunker Hill
triple culvert.
So, is a triple culvert.
It has been steadily deteriorating
for the last fifteen years.
This is something that should have been replaced a long time ago.
But it has not been because the town has not wanted to fund it.
We are
basically going for a temporary repair
to get us through until such point as
a full bridge replacement
can be done,
which should be starting sometime within the next eighteen months.
The,
as you are all probably aware,
so far this summer, we've had
three fairly significant flood events.
One of them was a ten year frequency
storm event.
One was a two year frequency storm event and the last one was a two hundred year frequency storm event.
And all three of those cases,
the water,
you know, twice
the water topped
the culvert itself
and ran over the culvert.
As many of you know,
to the north,
along the road, there's a low point in the road that that the water goes over the road first.
And then when the water gets about two feet deeper than that, the water actually goes over the culvert.
And
so, the big problem we have is culvert number three, which is the northernmost
culvert
has a bunch of fairly large holes in the bottom of the culvert. It's basically completely rusted out on the bottom,
and it is settled.
And
the problem is, is as
the
water gets higher in the velocity of the water increases,
the Venturi effect sucks the
sand
gravel mix out of the hole in the bottom of the culvert
and undermines the sides of the culvert, and you get sinkholes.
If you look at the picture, can I showed you basically where the two sinkholes
appeared?
So, what the town has done for an emergency fix
is they have dug,
staying within the concrete
head walls,
upstream and downstream,
they've dug out the film material.
And then first put down about six inch riprap, so basically heavy ballast stone,
filter fabric,
and then filled it back up with a very low strength concrete mixture called flowable fill.
So, there's nothing there to
disintegrate and wash out.
I realize we're doing this a little backwards,
although we submitted the wetlands application before we started,
you know, there was almost a month delay before the Wetlands Commission met.
And so, part of this work has been completed.
Public Works would still like to do the downstream side now, which the Board of Select has requested
before we
reopen Bunker Hill.
So,
we monitored very carefully to make sure that while construction was going, we weren't getting a lot of sediment in the river, and we were not. At the time we did it, the
water flow was very low,
and the stream continued to run clear.
We're not anticipating,
you know,
any
actual work in the river
without the consent of the Wetlands Commission.
The other area that's of concern
is if you see on that picture I'm showing,
says area of localized scour.
There's actually a scour hole on the head wall that extends below the concrete head wall, which means the head wall along the front and part of there is pretty well undermined and kind of structurally
not in the best of shape.
We would consider
using heavy balanced rock
in there to fill that scour hole to prevent
further undermining of the headwall in case we got another,
you know, high flow,
but that appears to be,
that would require permission
of the Welles Commission.
So,
in a nutshell, that's what we're talking about doing.
Does anybody on the Commission have any questions about that?
>> Okay, I don't have any questions about the work per se,
and I
certainly don't want to
delay
these absolutely necessary repairs.
I'm a little confused about
the item on the agenda, which is a jurisdictional ruling.
We don't, and I have not yet seen
an actual
application
for a wetlands
permit on this. Joe, could you comment on that?
I'm asking our agent, Joyce Wagner.
>> There should be a
permit posted online.
But if we're doing a jurisdictional
review, then it technically doesn't need to submit a permit yet
until you determine that
one one would be necessary.
>> From
my perspective, the jurisdiction is clear.
We already have precedent for
approval of a permit
for culvert activity on Hutchinson Road,
and I think this would fall under the same kind of rubric.
And again, as I say, we certainly want to see that work
completed as
expeditiously as possible
so that we can get more yokel throwing
barricades in the river.
Obvious impatience about getting across that
point
on the Hop River.
So
I think that we have jurisdiction
here.
And if we actually have a permit,
which again, I didn't see
at the time.
When I looked under applications submitted or pending
on the website, though, we don't have
an application on file there, so we're really getting our socks on over our shoes.
>> If we were It's going
listed under jurisdictional
reviews on the website,
which is under
>> It's on that sidebar, maybe. Oh, okay. Okay. So it was just a matter of where it was put.
>> And George, I brought up a copy on your screen of the wetlands
>> Yeah, I've got it here now too. Yeah,
okay. Okay, I'm sorry for the confusion because the agenda
didn't state that we actually had an application in hand,
and I hadn't noticed it
when I was looking for new application on the web.
Okay, So, since the motion on the floor is
to
determine whether or not we have jurisdiction,
let's knock that off.
And then
again, since this is our first meeting of actually
receiving
the application
under statute, we can't rule on it for fifteen days,
which means we'll have to have a special meeting
to
approve,
act on the permit application.
So,
that said,
let me
quickly poll the members so that we can get the jurisdictional review part out of the way,
and then we can move on to the applicant again
to
schedule a special meeting for the application.
So
Commissioner Larson,
your vote on the motion
to exercise jurisdiction.
Aye.
And
Commissioner Monroe.
Aye.
>> Okay, and Chairman
Eiliot also vote aye. So,
the Commission votes that we do have jurisdiction.
Now,
given the work is already underway and we expect it to proceed
with
further
issues that have arisen since I believe the application was submitted,
And as I said, under statutory
requirements,
we have to wait
before we can actually
vote on the motion.
So,
let's
take this opportunity
to
look at opportunities
for a special meeting.
Our next Well,
>> And because
we are running
over a week late in our normal cycle here,
I would like to ask Eric,
if we have a meeting in a little over two weeks,
is that much of a help as opposed to a little less than three weeks?
>> I was going to say that the earliest opportunity would be the twenty ninth
of this month, and our regular meeting would be October 4. So maybe we don't need, now that I'm looking at the calendar and with regard to Commissioner Larson's point,
it wouldn't
make much difference
in terms of time.
So, yeah, Eric, are you okay with that?
>> I'm okay with scheduling it for your next regular meeting,
with the caveat that
we are going to be doing further work on the bridge
probably starting next week, because we have to get the thing back open.
>> I figured as much, and
I
don't object personally,
and
I
would ask if any of the commissioners have any concerns
regarding,
again, having the town crew
working
on the bridge
and potentially
with the headwall
actually
depositing material in riverbed,
right?
>> I mean, that we don't have to do.
I mean, I would like to do that,
And we would actually consider going into the pipe by hand
and filling the void under the pipe with stone by hand.
You know, but that,
you know, that was definitely going to require wetlands approval before we did it. The
rest of the work, because we're not actually
disturbing the water course as we do this, because the water course is still running freely through the pipe.
All we're doing is resecuring
the pipe relative to the water course.
>> Right.
Okay, as long as the, okay, I haven't,
obviously
looked in detail at the application since I wasn't aware it was there. As
long as those issues are addressed in the application,
then, you know,
our consideration will include them.
And if they are faire complier,
then, well,
so be it.
I don't
see any issues here,
given
that we're talking about really an emergency repair
for
an
artery
and for a situation that's inconvenienced a lot of townsfolk.
Okay, any other comments or questions from
the Commission?
>> Chairman Elliot, I was wondering if,
since the repair he wants to do in the interim is
not affecting the water flowing through the culvert,
and it is kind of an emergency repair to get the bridge back open,
can
we have that take precedence over the two week wait?
I mean,
I don't know what we lose by approving it when the work is going to continue and we've got,
you know, Eric's
comment that he's not going to disturb the watercourse in the,
you know, he'll come back to the wetlands commission before he disturbs the watercourse. Yeah,
>> but the permit application
includes
the potential for
work in the watercourse per se, if it's, you know, again affecting the stream bed at the headwall
or
working in the culvert itself,
then that's clearly
within
the watercourse.
Not only, of course, is
the bridge itself,
is well within the 100 foot Upland Reviewer or the 200 foot Upland Reviewer area.
Correct.
>> So,
again,
I feel really uncomfortable with trying to shortcut
the timing,
which is statutory.
And
at the same time, we're on a quandary because we don't want to delay the work.
Major Wagner, do you have any comment on that,
situation?
>> Yeah. I was thinking,
initially that I could fall under
section 4.2 a of Landowners regulations,
where it could be permitted as a non regulated use.
This
4.2 a states that, conservation
of soil, vegetation, water,
fish, shellfish, and wildlife,
such operation or use may include, but is not limited to minor work to control erosion.
So I could I I just thought it would it could fall under that.
Because yeah. Controlling erosion.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
I could buy that. Because it's not in which is why I put it under jurisdictional review because if it if you did that, we could just say it's a permitted use because it's technically not
like, all the work that they're doing is inside those two head walls. It's they're not really doing anything work in the riverbed other than maybe a repair to the rusted out culvert
Right. Which is pretty minor, really.
The major work is removing all that fill, which is actually, like, isolated
from
the the stream itself by those two concrete
head walls.
>> Yeah.
A vexing problem there.
So
in essence, then what you would suggest
would require us to
rescind
the jurisdictional
ruling
and
state that the activity is permitted as of right.
>> I mean, either way, the result
will be the same. I mean, if you just approve the permit after the fact. I talked with, did I send you? I spoke with attorney Yeah, he
pretty much said that that was a kind of a standard practice to do after the fact permits for emergency repairs.
I mean, either way, if you believe that you have jurisdiction,
I mean, it's kind of fuzzy, make
a case either way.
So Yeah. I frankly, I'd rather exercise jurisdiction.
>> Yeah. And then just approve the permit at the next meeting if that's what you if that's what the commission wants to do, and then the end result's gonna be the same anyway.
>> Yeah, Again, the key here is we want to get the work done.
Yeah, we don't want to stand in the way of the work. Well, it still it still could be considered an emergency repair.
>> Yeah,
so
you know, I I I don't think we need to really
hold it up
is what I'm I'm trying to say, because it it could kinda fall under an emergency repair. I don't think anybody's gonna
argue with that.
>> I think when we pause the legal notice, we won't get any comment.
Okay,
so we'll leave it as is. We will take up
the permit application
at our next regular meeting,
and
I
believe that we have
adequate information
in the permit application to rule on it.
I'll ask,
the Commissioners on the call wanted to see further information
at the next meeting.
Any
details
of
either the activities
or the mitigation?
Not here.
I'm good. Doing.
>> Mean, the one thing I would say is that by
removing the sandy soil that's getting sucked out and replacing it with ballast rock,
we're actually decreasing
the sedimentation
that's going into the river. Now, every time it gets high. So, we're actually doing,
you know, the the repair
leads to a net
siltation of the river, a net
less
siltation of the river,
>> not increases it, or we could put it positively as a net improvement in water quality
downstream.
Okay,
I believe that's adequate consideration
of that
application,
and we will again return to that in our next regular meeting.
Thanks, Eric, for your
diligence on this issue.
Sure, thank you.
>> Okay,
the next item on the agenda, 6b,
we have a new permit application,
IWWC
from Brendan Wayne Fazino
for
property at 268 Lake Road,
rebuilding the existing lake wall
using existing and new stone
on the shoreline on Andover Lake. Again, that application
was online,
and
let's see now.
Abby, you could pull that up on screen.
Yep, bear with me a second.
Sure.
>> I don't have it handy at the moment. If you have it handy, can give you screen share,
>> or just wait for me to pull it up. Actually, I'm not working on this screen. I have
a setup where,
my main computer has got the materials
at hand,
and
the computer I'm using for the Zoom call is air gapped.
Okay.
So,
Okay, Commissioners, do you have this application in hand?
>> I did not run a copy off. I did look at it online before the meeting. Okay. Can you pull it up online
>> for the purpose of me? We're not going to be,
of course, again,
with the
statutory delay
between the receipt of the application and its actual ah, bravo.
Here There it we go.
So, the
application,
again, as you say,
was accompanied by
several
photographs
of the
existing condition
at a site plan.
>> Sorry about that. Did you want the pictures, or do you want to look at the site plan first? We could take a quick look at the pictures.
>> Okay.
And at this point, I'd like the
applicants if they have any comments on the situation.
>> Well,
that's
our existing wall. I think it was built in 1994.
And you can see it's getting a little tumbled down there. So we're
gonna have somebody take all the racks
out of the water, up on the lawn, and then rebuild the whole
wall
hopefully
this fall.
>> Okay.
As
the poet Frost put it, something there is that does not like a wall.
Indeed.
This is a usual,
not unusual situation.
It's almost reasonable.
>> There are a couple of questions I have for you
regarding the
site plan and, well, what I saw.
Have you
got a contractor
lined up
for this work?
Yes. Okay,
because usually we, in situations like this, we've typically had
a plan from the contractor
regarding
the mitigation,
and
that is to say what the what the contractor will be doing to avoid sedimentation
to avoid impact
on the lake and the lake bottom.
>> So well, asked him about that,
and
so on the site plan, I put where he's going to have his silt fences and the hay bales.
Those are
indicated there.
He was going to put a silt fence
on the lake bed itself.
And then up on the lawn, he was going to put a silt fence and line the whole thing with hay bales.
So there'd be a silt fence on both sides of the wall while he's working on it.
>> Okay,
the
second item I want. Okay,
so that's been addressed.
The second item,
do you have approval,
have an approval from the Andover Lake Management Association,
>> Alamo? No, I've been talking to Jeff Hayes on that and he was going to email that for this meeting,
but
there was personal
problems and he couldn't get everybody together to get
the online approval. So, I do not have the Alma approval yet. But it's in progress, and presumably by our next regular
meeting,
you will have that approval in hand.
>> Yep, he seemed pretty confident about that. Okay, very good. So,
>> that addresses
the two major concerns I had about the plan,
and I'll ask the members of the Commission
if they have any additional
concerns.
So, Judd,
Ristoff?
>> The,
well, the
concern I have is
about the pipe from the basement
that's running into the lake. Yep.
And
you wouldn't think in this I day and age that's what we were looking to
don't know what the pipe runs
into the lake,
but you wouldn't think that would be a best practice
for protecting the lake.
It's
been there forever.
>> So I understand that if we're gonna do
do work on it, maybe it's time to
make it so that it doesn't
drain whatever drains into the lake. Okay,
>> well, it's it's a the
house is
on dirt, it has a half cellar.
And when it rains, sometimes you get water in the cellar. And so there's a hole in the floor.
And the water runs down through the hole out the pipe and into the lake. That's, that's what that pipe is. So it's just a gravity drain from the basement floor?
Yes, yeah, for, for rainwater that gets in there.
That's what it is.
Okay.
What do you do instead of that?
>> Rebuild the house.
Okay.
That's
a good point,
Commissioner Eliza. I think that that's
something we might want to consider
in
mitigating the impact, and there might be
an efficient way to
>> Or the discharge from going directly to the lake. What we have seen on occasion is that the contractor that's building the wall, he puts a bunch of stone behind the wall with a
non permeable membrane or something, and it would almost be like a detention basin that you could run the pipe into that and it would sink into the ground as opposed to running into the lake.
>> Well,
you can see on the site plan that he is going to put
12 inches of crushed stone
behind the wall and line that with fabric.
So maybe if we run the pipe into that,
just that far,
is that what you're saying?
Yes,
>> the, you know, I Got a dumping right into the water,
>> dumping It would allow the
material to hopefully,
you know, sink into the ground as opposed to running into the lake. But if you're going to go through all that work to make that big trench,
which is what we would normally have you do up closer to the house, that
might be more costly.
But if we were to run that pipe into the high end of the stone so it can sink down in there, not go into the lake, that might be a better deal. Better, yeah, and better for the lake too, probably. Yes, yeah.
>> Why don't ask your contractor
about that? Okay. It would be,
you know.
>> Well, part of on
the permit part of what he's going to do is relay that
drainpipe
because
daddy put that in decades ago and it's it's worked up. It's kind of just sitting on top of the lawn now. So he's going to
dig
a trench to relay that pipe straighten it out so he could just go
to the crushed stone. Would be good.
>> Certainly be better. Yeah, absolutely. Yep. So the cellar drain pipe,
and then there's also indicated on that on the storm pipe,
which, okay, which runs from Lake Road. That comes from the road, yeah. Yeah,
yeah.
And again, that was
probably pre dates modern regulations.
That was Percy Cook.
Right.
>> Yeah, Percy Cook did that back in the, I think the 60s that was.
>> And
again,
not being
at all an authority on drainage systems,
you could ask your contractor, and I think also work with our agent,
to see if anything can be done to again redirect that discharge
from That's directly
into the
>> a that's a town thing.
That's there's
a town easement for that storm drain.
>> And
that's why I say the, you know, wetlands agent being,
you know, how shall I say, in the town hall,
might also be able to talk to other people about that, the easement, and whatever else is involved there.
>> So, you're talking about redirecting
the storm
pipe
away from the lake into
>> If there's a potential to do that, it seems to me that it would be
a good thing to do. Again, if it's not gonna
add tremendously
to the,
it would reduce
the impact on the lake for sure. It's
not something I would insist
that you undertake on your own recognizance,
especially if there's additional expense
involved there. But I think it's an idea to explore
at this point since we're still,
you know
>> I don't know if I can do anything about the storm pipe, because as I say, that's a town
thing, and we actually have an easement
where the pipe is for the town, and that we're not supposed to touch anything that's supposed to be town.
>> Right, but the discharge
goes through the wall
that you're proposing So, to
you know, there's going to have to be some impact
there. And as you say, I think that if
you talk to our wetlands agent and
the idea at the town hall level,
it might be possible to do something at this point.
You know,
the easement is obviously going to stay there, but
where exactly the discharge lands, whether it goes direct to the lake or whether it
has a chance to get filtered
first
is the question we have here
that
might be addressed.
>> It's
all underground.
A big 36 inches. It's a three foot pipe buried underground.
Right, but at the discharge end,
know, it's right,
>> it's coming through your
it's coming through your existing wall. Yes. So,
as I said, it seems to me there might be an opportunity
there.
>> Well, it's done.
Well,
I wouldn't mind getting rid of it.
>> Okay.
Okay, so
I'll direct our our wetlands agent to
look into
the potential
for remediation
there,
And we'll follow-up on that from
the Wellands Commission. Because again, I realize that since the easement is there,
it's a
town
facility,
if you will. It's
not really
in your
Not in my purview.
>> I can do about it. Yeah. Do you get a lot of flow through that during a rainstorm? Yeah. Well,
>> scours out under our dock a bit. We had to put some big
things
to block the flow. Otherwise, it would take our dock away every time we had a big storm.
>> Yeah. But
of it. With that amount of water, you would need some kind of retention basin or something, but that would, you know, that would probably take up half your yard.
That wouldn't really be a good a good alternative.
Anything that was too restrictive would would back up the drainage.
>> Right. The storm
drain is fed by several other storm drains on the street and
we're at the sort of at the bottom of a hill and the hill pretty much drains into there. Once it rains with Ida,
it was draining into the storm drain for days. It took quite a long time for all the water to come off the hill and go through the pipe.
>> It seems like a like an awful short stretch to
have any kind of measures to infiltrate that that amount of water. But, I mean, I can I can ask,
see if anyone has any suggestions? I just,
looking at it now, it seems like it'd be hard to come up with some kind of
thing that wouldn't turn your yard into
drainage
Which we also want to avoid.
Right.
>> I mean, it's like you'd have to dig up the street and connect the storm drain over towards Scoogs Brook.
You know,
>> something. Doesn't change anything. Yeah, which Running doesn't really change
full enough, we don't need to raise the level over there.
>> Right, yeah. I mean, it's all this water and what do you do with it? Yep.
>> I think it's a stretch too but
Agent Wagner wants to
look into it a little bit, that's great. Wonderful,
okay. Yeah,
>> see if anybody has any
idea
and I'll get back to you. Good.
Thank you. Okay.
>> Any other questions
or concerns
about the application?
In other words,
it's our chance to put an order in before we have to really consider it formally.
This is all pre
preliminary
discussion,
really.
Okay.
Okay,
if we don't have any further
questions or comments,
I'd like to move on to the agenda. And as I say, we will return to this application
at our next regular meeting where we'll be able to formally consider
the application
for approval.
Good. Thank you. Okay.
>> And, again,
understanding that you have addressed already
the major concerns
and the things we're talking about now, mitigation of stormwater runoff from the road and from the cellar
are,
again
simply items that we would like to consider. They may or may not be possible to do anything about them.
>> I did have one question.
The
builder wanted me to ask, is it okay if he brings equipment down? Like he has a small excavator
that he would use to pick up the rocks and move them around. Is that allowable, or does he have to do it all by hand?
>> We have allowed
equipment,
and I think that the
issues there would again be the same:
avoidance of sedimentation and impact on the lake bottom
and
being nice to your yard while he's at it. So, perhaps using,
you know, using
four by eight plywood,
things like that, as a support
for the equipment,
putting in mulch as a temporary track
for the equipment treads.
But there's
certainly no
bar
on using equipment per se.
It's just, again, a matter of avoiding
being careful about
erosion.
Okay. Yep.
Alright. Good. Thank you.
>> Agent Wagner, did you have any other comment on that question?
>> No, I mean, looking at that yard when I went to take those pictures,
it's not.
It's not a steep yard.
It's pretty gradual slope down there. It doesn't look like a a real
high erosion risk.
Especially since that storm drain channel a lot of the water under the lawn.
But, yes,
I I don't see a small excavator,
probably too much of an issue, and we can address that if it does cause problem.
Okay.
Well, good. Thank you. I'll tell them that. Okay.
>> One last thing from my notes here.
I wonder if any of the commission feels that a sidewalk
would be particularly
useful here.
In my view, the the photographs
are
adequate to represent the condition, and the site plan tells us what they're gonna wanna do.
Jed, do you still have sidewalk or
>> would you rather kayak in? Yeah. I I don't think I need a sidewalk.
Okay,
Mr. Monroe.
I'll kayak in. Okay.
>> We're off by the beach. Check it out from the lakeside. All right.
Okay, then I think that that
takes care of that item on the agenda,
and I'd like to move on again. I'm carefully
watching the time, and we've got some
items that
could take some serious time.
The
Okay, thank you. We're out now. Okay, very good.
>> Very excused.
Hold on a second.
Okay, item seven on the agenda. Any enforcement actions,
Agent Wagner?
I don't see any listed. Yeah, it's nothing
this month. That's good. Good news.
No enforcement is good enforcement.
Okay, next item, eight: revision of our regulations.
Now, we have
two items
subheaded here. The first is revision of the standard
permit conditions.
Now, Adrian Weiner, you distributed,
I believe, a draft
for the
standard conditions.
I have a document.
>> Yeah. I think I sent it to you, and then you,
you sent it to the commission last week, maybe.
>> I remember seeing it. Yeah. That my yeah. Exactly. I,
sent that and some other
regulation revisions.
So,
let's see here. Can you bring that up? Again, I'm not able to do that on my computer, screen share that.
And then if you could describe what
changes there may be or what we've done. I will comment to the Commission that this has been through
review by Attorney Brandts.
>> Can
so I can screen share. Let's see if I can remember how to do that.
>> Just need you a co host, so you should see a green screen share at the bottom of your screen. Oh, okay.
>> Let's see.
Try and find it first.
Make sure I share the right one.
Alright.
Everybody see that?
>> Yep. You could bump up the size of the document
a little bit. I
maybe make it about a 150%.
There you go. That worked.
>> This is
this is the one with the
changes,
that Mark Brandt suggested.
I'll show you this one so you could see what's different about it. He went and reviewed ours and then, updated it to reflect
law
and any
suggestions that
that he had.
So condition number four will be changed.
There's some reasons. I looked at it a while ago, but there's some
stuff on the back. I can pass this along to the commission if they wanna review it before the next meeting because I feel like this will be a multi month process.
>> Well,
again, my understanding is this is this new clause is simply
the result of
action by the General Assembly in the last legislative session.
The
legislature in his wisdom decided to extend certain
permits
up to like 14 meters,
which
is a lot of grandfathering in my opinion, but
there we go.
So
It's not like we're really in a position to make revisions in any event.
>> Yeah. Once again, he recommends
using standard conditions.
Then he recommends putting any conditions on the plan, which
I added to the
final version of that, which I think George sent to you guys.
I'm not sure if this falls under
the whole regulation revision because it's it's standard
condition. It's something that the commission just adds, but we could wait to implement it until after we get our regulations revised to make sure.
>> Right. So so
okay. So standard condition for bonding,
would follow from regulations.
Yeah. Yeah.
K.
I'll have to look at that again.
Basically, we'd
like to get these and our regulations updated
as soon as possible.
However,
as soon as possible may be a while,
given the nature of the
process.
If I could speak to that, we have
essentially,
I'm not sure
if
the
proposed revisions of the regulations
actually require
review and hearing. I'm going to ask
I'm going to contact
DEEP
about it.
Let me find the specific
At some point, we came into possession of amendment
timeline.
I'm not sure what we're doing. The revisions constitute
amendments.
We're not
coming up with any new regulations.
We're simply revising our regulations
according to
the model
provided by DEEP
and
in accordance with state statutes.
But
let's say
DEEP regards these as amendments.
In that case,
we would have to have review
in a public hearing,
and we would have to submit
the
proposed amendment
at least thirty five days
before
a hearing
were to be held, and we would have to have a hearing within sixty five days.
So,
within
that,
we would have to then submit the final
adopted amendment
to DEP within ten days.
So, there's a minimum of
over a month
between the time
that we
submit
regulations for approval
and the time that we can have a hearing.
And then, once the hearing
is held, we
could potentially approve
the revisions.
So, as I said, the first step, and what I will do following this meeting,
is to contact DEEP
with respect to whether or not they consider
what we're doing to be technically amending the regulations
or simply revising them in accordance with updates
to
the model that we're following and the
state
requirements,
such as the
grace period and the, you know, the expiration of permits under certain conditions.
So,
given that, it's unrealistic
to think that we could have a hearing
before
our December meeting
and
possibly January.
I don't think we would have to have a hearing,
know, a standalone hearing. I think we could have a hearing
that would
precede
our regular meeting,
thus allowing us to act on the subject
after the hearing.
So, we have the hearing,
we adjourn the hearing,
We go to the regular meeting.
We have the revisions as an agenda item.
So,
at this point,
I guess all we can do is see if we have any concerns
about
the proposed
revisions,
which would affect our standard conditions,
as Agent Wagner just pointed out,
and whether we have any
further
need to amend our regulations.
So,
again, in alphabetical order and in screen order, Judd, do you have any
questions or comments
about the standard conditions or regulations
and the revisions that we're proposing?
>> I have no comments or questions on the revisions you're proposing. I do have two
questions to make sure that,
but I'm working on the process issue for planning and zoning that I
like the standard conditions thing.
I'm planning to plagiarize that at some point here.
But
I did have a comment on item seven on the list, which is all activities for the prevention of soil erosion.
And
I'm probably
begging you just a little Joe here, I talked to Jim about it the other day and he may not have had a chance to talk to you before he took off,
but I know at 436
Lake Road
the sediment
fencing
got washed
away by the sediment
on the first of the big storms we've had.
And it does not appear to me that anybody has taken any action to fix that over there.
And I know you were on-site not too long ago, I guess, checking out trees that they wanted to cut
down. But
my concern is that
the erosion,
our requirement is it's checked weekly and after rains
and I don't think it's being checked at all
and I don't know if we have some process to,
you know, it says that the engineer will do that. And
do we get these reports from that?
Kind of like we weren't getting the reports on the gravel pit and, you know, all of a sudden that got to be a big problem there at the end.
But anyhow,
I'll let you take a look at that.
The piece of the fence that I can see from when I'm walking by it on the road, you know, is
severely washed away.
May be others, I just can't see it from that.
>> Yeah. That there's
that section. What is it? It's like 15
feet from the road, maybe. Yep. Yeah. I've seen I've I haven't been there in the past couple weeks.
Probably should have after that last rain.
But I have they have been pretty cooperative.
I've been going back there with all this rain. I I visited the site like three or four times probably, and then in
the back, they had a big mulch barrier in combination with
with the sediment fence, and we've we've moved some stuff around. They put hay bales,
fixed the fence a few times.
They put a little a little, like, retention pool back there to slow the the water down. So they've been pretty good, pretty responsive with
>> with that. So, judge, your question is not about the the regulation per se, but making sure that it that it gets.
>> Yeah, I would have just expected that to have been fixed after the first big rain and
didn't see it.
And I guess the last one,
on item nine,
it says these standard conditions,
along with any special conditions contained in the approval motion
shall be reproduced in full on final plans, which final plan shall be endorsed by the Commissioner or its agent prior to the commencement of any regulated
activity.
And
I guess my question is,
are you guys doing that now?
And I'm finding over in planning and zoning,
maybe there's some confusion,
especially with the applicants, that when we give approval
at the
planning and zoning meeting, they think they're done. And they've got
a bunch of other work that has to get done before it's really done. And I don't think we've been doing as good a job as explaining what they need to do
and making sure that it gets done. And I think we've got some open
permits that we might have to go work on getting to conclusion.
>> Yeah, it's not.
Mean, it's it's encouraged, but it's not usually a condition of of the the permit approval now,
which is why I thought it would be a good addition and and. Okay, so that's an addition you're putting in there. Yeah, so that's a new a new thing. Yep, nope, because I know
>> that on, you know, like 12 Webster Lane,
there was on the mylars, I went in and signed it, there was a place for the
wetlands
commissioner
chair.
But I don't know that we have signed the mylars
for
Pine Ridge Road And that's the one I got to go pull the string on. I don't think I've signed anything on that.
And so is there, you know, I think the applicants,
they got approval at planning and zoning, approval from wetlands, they think they're good to go.
And
not true.
And so
if that's an ad you're putting in there, I think it's a great one. And
now we just have to make sure that we track getting those things finished after we granted approval.
Because the applicants all go away happy that they don't know they're not done yet. And if it's if they're not aware of it, then it's
>> really not. It's not on them, guess. By putting it on there, think it'll. Okay. Nope. I think that's a great addition then. It'll be coming out. And to the extent of my comments.
Okay.
You, Commissioner Larson. Commissioner Monroe.
>> I'll have to I'll have to read this over. I mean, I've read through it, but I've mostly perused it and,
I'm just getting it a
little bit. Not,
even what Jed was just talking about, I didn't even
I didn't really understand what was going on there, but
I got it.
I got Okay.
>> I read it, but
it doesn't all stick in there the way I'd like it to. It takes a while, Bill.
It doesn't do. You're
>> just starting to figure out the planning and zoning piece.
Complicated.
>> Takes a while for the light bulb to come on.
Yeah, the light bulb is very dim right now.
>> So,
okay, so we're
essentially, we're good with the
standard conditions
with the caveat that
there might be
a regulatory
aspect to the bond
condition,
and that might have to be addressed in our regulations.
As far as the regulations
themselves,
again, as we stated, the
revisions
are
complete,
to the best of my knowledge.
We incorporated the new
language
provided
by
Hallor and Sage, particularly Attorney Brantz and his colleagues
regarding
the new
statutory
language.
And as far as I'm aware, everything else in our regulations
comes from the
DEEP
model regulations
and
direct from state statutes.
So, I asked some questions about language that I considered
confusing
about the requirement for hearings.
And well, no, that's what the statute says.
So, really, we don't have any
leeway
to
change that language.
So, if there are no questions for no further questions about the proposed
changes,
again, I distributed
those along with the draft of the regulations and the draft of the
standard
conditions.
>> I will say George that
I did read through all the changes
and similar to what
Commissioner Monroe just said about the checklist,
you know, I understood changing DEP
to DEEP,
but when you got down to all this stuff about
easements and the protected areas
and all that stuff going back to that,
my eyes kind of glazed over and You mean all of Section 125,
120 Yeah, I do.
>> Likewise. I do a better job when we actually have an example to work through than trying to figure out what that said. I couldn't get anything out of it.
>> So I just put on record, Jean. I got no comments on it other than the fact that Well, I would say that the odds of our ever being confronted with a situation where any of those conditions applies
are pretty slim. That was my takeaway.
>> And
actually, it's my hope
that we will never have to encounter
any applications in which these regulations
are
relevant.
>> I guess if we do, we'll go talk to attorney branch.
>> Exactly.
That's what we have a retainer for.
So
as I said, I'm going to
inquire. I'll contact
whoever
is responsible at DEEP and
see if I can find out
what we need to do next.
If we do need to have
a hearing,
as I said, we will probably not be able to schedule it before
our December meeting
and probably January,
so we can
discuss
that on our October meeting.
Sounds good.
>> Okay.
Alright. And we will move on now
to the next item on the agenda,
which if I can find it again.
I have so many layers of document on my desktop that it takes a while to
scroll
through them.
Okay. Right. Time now for agent report. There are several administrative
permits.
Yeah. I can, I just quickly go
>> just quickly going through,
some pretty
straightforward ones? There was a shed rebuilt.
It was demolished and rebuilt
on 27 Hendy Road.
The the tree clearing,
limited number of marked trees, I think there was pictures online.
They could view for the four thirty six Lake Road application.
I visited the site with the
applicant and we ensure we pretty much made sure that
only the marked trees will be cut and they're gonna be cut with a chainsaw
and a lot of the wood is gonna be left there. And then
what isn't gonna be left there is gonna be carried out by hand or wheelbarrow.
So there's no no equipment in that area.
Once we got
119 Lakeside Drive,
it was a a generator and
gas tank installation,
propane gas.
So that was along the house. Let's see.
Then there was a
kind of after the fact permit
for a paver driveway that was the work was started, and then I had to get in touch with them and go
through the process.
So it was an existing gravel driveway, then pavers was installed
were installed over
the old driveway footprint. So it wasn't as expanded at at all. But
so that one was 159 Lakeside.
And then the last one, 22 Bailey Road was the guy was getting a foundation replaced.
And now they're using the concrete rubble to
construct a little ramp on an old farm road in their backyard.
So it was pretty pretty
simple project. It was within the 100 foot upland review area, but as well out of Stream channel. And and,
yeah, like I said, it was along an old road
that was back there when when it was a farm.
So that's that's it for the report.
Anybody have any questions?
>> I was gonna ask you about the first one, Bill Monroe.
That that construction
or reconstruction,
It's got to be outside
of the flood zone, right?
>> It's it's
up on. Yeah, if you're familiar with the site, there's a like a flat area and then it goes up
a steep embankment and then, the shed that he
demolished and replaces up above that. So it's like right on the edge of the 200 foot up on review area.
I think it was,
I think it was around a 180 feet from the river.
So
>> Alright. Because I noticed that you had a whole bunch of stuff down there right by the river and I appreciate
>> it. Yeah. Right? Yeah. And there was a there's another building down there. But, this was a different building up up further away.
Yeah.
>> Okay, any other questions or comments about the agent report?
Okay,
so did
get a
was there any
any documentation on that other than the application?
I didn't see that online.
Twenty one eighteen?
Yeah.
>> Let's see.
Might be on
take a look at the Okay. There's
a there's a description.
Yeah.
>> He has a a site plan on there. I know that. I don't know if I put any pictures on there. I think I took some pictures. I don't know if I posted them. No, I don't see any pictures. That's okay. I just wondered. They weren't very. It was hard to see with
the pictures. I think that's why I didn't put them on there. They wouldn't really give you much.
Yeah. That's why I didn't post that one.
>> Okay.
Well, we're within minutes of the time that I need to wrap up.
So,
other business review of
permit link application and documents.
I believe that the gist of this is that we're going to be going online
with all of our applications.
Right?
>> Yeah. Sometime, Sue. Not yet, but we're
I just wanted to
run the documents by the commission to make sure they didn't want me to add or change anything
before I submitted
them to the permanent link company.
So I had sent George. Did I send I don't know if I sent them to the commission
or if I sent them just to the chairman.
>> Yeah. I I looked at it, I didn't see any need to
make any changes since, you know, our we're
trying to keep our application process simple. I don't think we're looking for
we wouldn't be looking for extensive changes
to the standard format that they offer.
And
I think probably at this point, you
should
go ahead and share
it with the other commissioners.
I
don't know that the commission review is gonna be required
to adopt this, but at least we should review it before we
take the next step.
>> Alright. I'll, yeah, I'll email everything I have so far out.
It's basically the the any information that was on the like helpful information
for
providing adequate detail on the application
because the the the new one is only two pages.
So I pulled that information off of our old application and kinda cleaned it up, and we'll put it on the website
that you go to to get to the permit link. So you'll be able to review all that stuff
pretty much the same. So it'll be good. It'll be pretty similar. Just a little different layout.
>> Okay,
well then,
that concludes our business
for the regular
meeting.
Our next regular meeting will be Monday, October 4, at 7PM,
hopefully not so constrained by time,
and by unanimous consent, we're going to adjourn this meeting
at 08:15.
Abby, our new board clerk, I
appreciate your
being here and helping to run the meeting.
You'll have to update your screen icon. Otherwise, we'll all think that you're Amanda's twin sister.
But again, pleasure to see you here, and I look forward to seeing you next month. So, with that, I'm going to leave the meeting because I have to get on my way to Bradley Airport.
Good night all. Good night, everybody. Thank Good
night, everyone.
Bye.